We are on דף כג Daf Kaf-Gimmel 23 and at the very
top starting at the very beginning of the דף. Daf. The issue
that we have been dealing with is a fascinating question. These משניות
Mishnayot from now to the end of the פרק Perek deal with,
you know, what's good for A is not good for B, what's
good for B is not good for A.
And the גמרא Gemara is exploring the question about things that fall
sort of between the two. It's what Aristotle called the excluded middle.
It's, you know, the opposite. I've said this before, the opposite of
A is not B. The opposite of chocolate is not vanilla. The
opposite of A is not A, right? The opposite of chocolate is
anything that's not chocolate. So if you define the world in terms
of chocolate and vanilla, you have to ask: what about everything that's
not chocolate or vanilla? So anyway, our... that's the question our גמרא
Gemara has been asking, specifically around this issue about the birds. Bird
קרבנות, Korbanot, whether they are turtle doves or pigeons, depends. The turtle
doves have to be adults, the pigeons have to be children. What
about this stage in the middle where the feathers start getting bright
or yellow, which is תחילת הציהוב? Tchilat Hatzihuv? What about this stage
which is what we call adolescence, right? So is adolescence... is it
that you're in adulthood or childhood? We just don't know how to
categorize it, but the world really is divided into those two categories,
or no, maybe the world is not divided into those two categories,
maybe it is a third category that is neither one nor the
other. So the way the גמרא... Gemara... and this can obviously be
applied to many areas which we will do today. The way the
גמרא Gemara asks this question was if somebody brings... says, "I will
bring a קרבן Korban either of turtle doves or of pigeons, either
of תורים Torim or בני יונה," Bnei Yona, and then brings both
turtle doves and pigeons, each one of them at the stage of
adolescence, at the stage of תחילת הציהוב. Tchilat Hatzihuv. Do we say
definitely one of them was right, definitely one of them was either
an adult or a child, or do we say no, both of
them were wrong because that middle stage is neither adulthood or childhood?
Okay, so that's the גמרא's Gemara question. And it tried to say
that because we needed a פסוק Pasuk to exclude this period of
תחילת הציהוב, Tchilat Hatzihuv, that showed that it was this separate category
because if it was just a doubt, that would be our doubt
and we would figure out how to resolve it, you would not
need a פסוק. Pasuk. And now the גמרא Gemara is saying not
necessarily true. Maybe the פסוק Pasuk is an אסמכתא, Asmachta, or it
is true that you wouldn't need a פסוק Pasuk if it was
just an issue of a doubtful categorization, but the פסוק Pasuk maybe
was with an אסמכתא Asmachta and the real purpose of the פסוק
Pasuk was not to exclude the category of תחילת הציהוב Tchilat Hatzihuv
of adolescence in birds, but it was to exclude other problematic states
of birds. So let's take a look. Top of כג עמוד א.
Kaf-Gimmel Amud Aleph.
כי אצטריך קרא, Ki itztarich kra, what was the פסוק Pasuk needed
for? למיעוטי נרבע ונעבד. Lemiutei nirva vene'evad. So yes, you needed a
פסוק Pasuk to exclude certain types of birds, but not birds in
this period of תחילת הציהוב Tchilat Hatzihuv of adolescence. Those are excluded
because we just don't know, are they adults, are they children? That's
our doubt and maybe is not its own category. So what is
the פסוק Pasuk excluding? The פסוק Pasuk is excluding other types of
birds, birds that were used in an act of bestiality, interesting, or
birds that were worshipped. Now those are clearly invalid for sacrifices. Those
are clearly invalid if they're mammals, large animals, that we know as
a very fundamental category of invalid animals. Why would I think that
it would be different by birds? So here's it's going to tell
me why. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach amina, I would have thought
to say, הואיל וכתיב, Ho'il uchitiv, since the פסוק Pasuk says by
blemishes, by animals, that they cannot be brought as sacrifices,
כי משחתם בהם מום בם, Ki moshchatam bahem mum bam, because their
corruption, yeah, corruption I don't know, but anyway, somehow...
that's the way it's used to be...
corruption, okay. So somehow their defilement is in them, their blemish is
in them, so therefore they cannot be brought as sacrifices. Now that's
talking about physical blemishes, but the מדרש Midrash says the extra emphasis
of משחתם בהם Moshchatam bahem is expanding the category beyond physical blemishes.
ותנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Vetana devei Rabbi Yishmael, we taught in the
house of Rabbi Yishmael, כל מקום שנאמר השחתה, Kol makom shene'emar hashchata,
wherever the פסוק Pasuk speaks about השחתה, Hashchata, to corrupt, אינו אלא
דבר ערוה ועבודת כוכבים, Eino ela devar erva va'avodat kochavim, is either
talking about immoral sexual behavior or idolatry. דבר ערוה דכתיב, Devar erva
dechtiv, how do I know it's talking about, you know, illicit sexual
behavior? Because it says כי השחית כל בשר את דרכו על הארץ,
Ki hishchit kol basar et darko al ha'aretz, because all flesh, right,
before the flood of נח, Noach, all flesh had corrupted its way
on the land. So you don't exactly know there that it's referring
to illicit sex, but again, certainly it's suggested by the emphasis of
כל בשר, Kol basar, of flesh, so it's a sin of the
flesh. And based on other sort of
מדרשים, Midrashim,
there's an assumption that the sin of the דור Dor of נח
Noach was relating to sexual sins, or one of the sins. So
therefore that's how we see the idea of השחית Hishchit corrupt means
to sin sexually. עבודת כוכבים, Avodat kochavim, how do we know it
means idolatry? דכתיב, Dechtiv, because it says פן תשחיתון ועשיתם לכם פסל,
Pen tashchitun va'asitem lachem pesel, lest you... Act corruptly and makes for
yourself any image. As I've discussed before on other occasions, you know,
the Torah refers to the prohibition of idolatry in two ways or
uses two images or imageries. One is like,
you know, זנות, zenut, it actually does use the imagery of, interestingly,
of illicit sexual behavior, right? It says וקם העם הזה וזנה אחרי
אלהי נכר הארץ. vekam ha'am hazeh vezanah acharei elohei nechar ha'aretz. This
nation will fornicate after the gods of the lands. Or God is
אל קנא, El Kana, God is a jealous God like the jealous
husband, you know, when his when the wife is suspected of committing
adultery. So there very commonly you have that imagery. The other imagery
you have is the word of השחתה, hashchatah, to corrupt. פן תשחיתון.
pen tashchitun. By חטא העגל cheit ha'eigel it says כי שחת עמך.
ki shicheit amcha. And I believe that this is really describing two
different forms of עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. One form of עבודה זרה
Avoda Zara is לא יהיה לך אלהים אחרים על פני, lo yihyeh
lecha elohim acherim al panai, כי אנכי ה' אלהיך אל קנא. ki
anochi Hashem elokecha El Kana. It is having other gods. It's, you
know, sort of if you would, it is, you know, it's fornicating
after other gods. It is, it is, you know, it is violating
the fidelity of the relationship and consorting with other gods, having relationships
with other gods. Okay, so that is about abandoning God and worshipping
other gods, and there the imagery is that of זנות. zenut. However,
there's another form of עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, which is the worship
of God through images. And that's what the verse is referring to
here in דברים Devarim where it says פן תשחיתון ועשיתם לכם פסל,
pen tashchitun ve'asitem lachem pasel,
where it says you did not see any image of הר סיני,
Har Sinai, right? That's the context of this. You remember that you
did not see any image when God gave you the Torah. Therefore,
do not act corruptly and make an image. So the image is
not a worship of another god, it is the attempt to embody
God in something physical. It is the attempt to worship God through
images. And therefore the proper imagery there is not that of זנות,
zenut, of adultery and fornication, it is that of השחתה. hashchatah. You
are worshipping God, but you are corrupting the idea of God. You
are corrupting the worship of God. So that's here the word השחתה
hashchatah is used in that context.
Yes. Saying that that you would be told that worshipping any other
god but השם Hashem is fornicating, that's some form of fornication?
That is the imagery, yes.
That's
and and by השם Hashem would not say worshipping השם Hashem is
a form of fornication.
Right,
it's you could corrupt the worship of God, but it is not
would not use the imagery of of fornication. Fornication is that you
abandon your mate and you consort with another person, right? So you
abandon God and you consort with other gods.
Okay so that's it's very metaphorical.
Yeah, yeah. I mean, the whole question here is the metaphor being
used. Right.
What do you do about the people who say like גזלה gezelah
פחות משוה פרוטה? pachot mishaveh perutah? How does that fit in there?
What? Oh, about דור המבול. Dor Hamabul. Well, that's not the only
sin of דור המבול. Dor Hamabul. But anyway, within this context, this
תנא Tanna
is assuming השחתה hashchatah is not necessarily referring to, I don't know.
Anyway, that they learn out from not the word השחתה, hashchatah, but
the word חמס. chamas. קץ כל בשר,
keitz kol
basar, חמס.
chamas. Okay. Anyway, all right. So the גמרא Gemara says, so therefore
those are the two things that are being referred to. And therefore
what's the relevance of this?
That therefore we know, so פן תשחיתון ועשיתם לכם פסל, pen tashchitun
ve'asitem lachem pasel, כל שמום פוסל בו דבר ערוה ועבודת כוכבים פוסל
בו. kol shemum posel bo devar ervah va'avodat kochavim posel bo.
So here it says their corruption is in them, their blemish is
in them. So what does it mean? It means that animals are
blemished, are invalid, not just with a physical blemish, but with something
that is considered a השחתה, hashchatah, a corruption. So if an animal
is used in idolatry, it's worshipped as an idol, or if an
animal is used in an act of sex, therefore it also becomes
invalid, a type of a blemish. But now says the גמרא, Gemara,
that's all because it's been compared to the idea of blemish. משחתם
בהם מום בם. moshchatam bahem mum bam. Their השחתה, hashchatah, their corruption
is a blemish. So I might have thought to say the following:
כל שמום פוסל בו דבר ערוה ועבודת כוכבים פוסל בו. kol shemum
posel bo devar ervah va'avodat kochavim posel bo. Whenever a physical blemish
is in invalidates, therefore these other problems about idolatry and sex, you
know, done to the animal, also invalidate. וכל שאין מום פוסל בו.
vechol she'ein mum posel bo. But if you have a type of
an animal that physical blemishes are not a problem, אין דבר ערוה
ועבודת כוכבים פוסל בו. ein devar ervah va'avodat kochavim posel bo. So
maybe by analogy, other of these other non-physical but more, you know,
moral problems also do not invalidate. So physical blemishes don't invalidate, so
similarly an animal used in idolatry or used in illicit sex also
would not invalidate since they're all being compared. And therefore, and how
is this relevant? והני עופות, vehani ofot, and when it comes to
birds, הואיל ולא פסלי בהו מומא, ho'il velo paslei behu muma, since
we know that physical blemishes do not invalidate by birds. How do
you know that? דאמר מר, de'amar mar, because we teach, תמות וזכרות
בבהמה ואין תמות וזכרות בעופות. tamut vezachrut bebiheimah ve'ein tamut vezachrut be'ofot.
The Torah says by animals, it says it says זכר
תמים, zachar tamim, where what's the פסוק? pasuk?
Hold on.
Wait, wait, wait. תמים זכר. tamim zachar. It says let's see, I'm
forgetting the פסוק pasuk here. It says תמים זכר בבקר בכשבים ובעזים,
tamim zachar babakar bakesavim uv'izim,
you know, unblemished and male. And then it lists all the... animals,
but it doesn't mention birds. So the תורה Torah when it mentions
the larger animals always speaks about being unblemished, תמים. Tamim. It never
uses the word תמים Tamim when it speaks about birds. Now not
all animal sacrifices have to be male. Some can be females as
well, like in a שלמים, Shelomim, etc., or חטאת. Chatas. But some
animals must be male. And those concepts, where the תורה Torah never
demands when it talks about birds, never speaks about their unblemished state
and never speaks about their sex—never speaks about whether male or female,
never speaks about their unblemished state. So the גמרא Gemara says very
reasonably that those are not issues by birds. Birds don't have to
be unblemished, it doesn't matter male or female; those are not issues.
So since that's true, if physical blemishes are not a problem, it
stands to reason that these issues, right, used in sex, used in
idolatry, is also not a problem. So therefore you need one minute—therefore
you also need the פסוק passuk to teach. So אימא... Eima... okay,
so I might think ורבעה ועבודת כוכבים נמי לא לפסלו בהו? v'reva
v'avodat kochavim nami lo lifselu behu? So used in sex and an
idolatry also should not invalidate birds? קא משמע לן, Kamashmalan, so it
teaches otherwise, it teaches that it does invalidate by birds. Now, Michael's
a little bit upset because he knows that by birds it's not
true that there's never a problem; there is a problem called מחוסר
אבר Mechussar eiver if it's missing an entire limb. So there's a
question, that is true, but there's first of all a conceptual question
whether the problem of a bird missing a limb is seen as
a type of a blemish. But just the definition of מום Mum
has a higher threshold by birds, right? מום Mum maybe is a
problem but not small little blemishes, only a big thing like missing
a limb. Or is it seen as a categorically different problem? רש"י,
Rashi, for example, although תוספות Tosafot argues, says the problem of missing
a limb is based on a verse of הקריבהו נא לפחתך—would Hakrivehu
na l'pachatecha you bring this as a gift to, you know, an
officer, an important person? So it's not a technical blemish; it's just
like פאסט נישט—it's Pashnisht not appropriate. But it's a different type of
a category. Or maybe it's just a category called מחוסר אבר, Mechussar
eiver, but not a type of a blemish. And that might in
a way be part of the answer, because in the answer we
actually have a fascinating point, which is that by birds, physical blemishes
don't matter, but more of these sort of moral or religious blemishes
do matter. So that, by the way, is interesting because sometimes, at
least for me, you know, a problematic aspect about the whole emphasis
on מום, Mum, less by animals, more by the כהנים—but, Kohanim you
know, a problematic aspect is the emphasis on the external and the
physical rather than on the things that we would think from a
religious perspective really matter,
right, like issues like morality and ethics and so on. And here
you're seeing by birds, actually, that we're willing to ignore physical blemishes,
but these problems are considered the bigger problems. Even though not mentioned
in the verse, right, these are the bigger problems and these problems
remain an issue by birds. Or could be birds also big physical
blemishes are also an issue, but the point is these in the
end are more weighty. I might have wanted to categorize them in
the same way, but in the end I'm being told, no, these
are more weighty. Yes.
Very difficult to tell the sex of a bird.
Interesting. My daughter has a parrot that they thought was a male
and then it laid eggs.
Why is that?
And in order to—certain types of parrots, some birds like parakeets, they
have different colored beaks.
So you can tell, but...
They don't have genitalia, birds?
Not outer. Interesting. So only—it's internal.
And
how do the eggs get fertilized?
Well, they didn't—they... I don't know, but...
I wish...
That's very interesting.
I don't know. I mean, I know that happened with my daughter
and the vet said in order to determine the sex, it's an
expensive process.
Wow, wow, very interesting. Certain species.
Right. I know it was with parrots.
Right, right, right.
So you're saying is that in some ways you would have thought
that מום Mum and עבודה זרה—I'm Avodah zarah coming from the perspective
that נרבע ונעבד Nirva v'ne'evad would be like obviously wrong instead of
saying you would have thought that wouldn't have been...
No, it's saying I would have thought that by birds since blemishes
are not a problem, these are not a problem. Yeah, but the
verse teaches you that they are. So which is very nice, which
means at the end of the day, these moral issues, if you
will, are bigger deals, matter more, bigger blemishes than mere physical blemishes.
Right, I would have thought it's kind of obvious, like you know,
if it was worshipped as another god...
Well, that's very nice that you would have thought it's obvious, but
the interesting thing is that the פסוקים Pesukim don't talk about these
other things. The פסוקים Pesukim only talk about physical blemishes. So in
a way, it's very nice that what we're doing is we're surfacing
the point that there are other things which are equally as important
as physical blemishes, not only equal, even more important. So I'm glad
to hear that your sort of religious and ethical intuition is in
line with this, but if you were strictly a literalist in terms
of the פסוקים, Pesukim, you would have said the פסוקים Pesukim only
care about physical blemishes, right? So you should be very happy with
that conclusion. Okay, so what?
בני יונה Bnei yonah just means young.
Yeah, exactly. Okay, so therefore that's what the verse is doing. It's
excluding that, and not necessarily excluding this stage of adolescence. So we're
back to our question, which is what is the story with this
stage of adolescence of birds? Is it that it is adulthood or
childhood, we just don't know which, or that it is actually its
own category? And again, the difference
would
be... ask very similar questions by other areas as well about is
this is a middle stage genuine a different stage or just we
don't know how to categorize it. בעי Ba'ei Reb Zeira, so רב
זירא Reb Zeira asks, אומר הרי עלי עולת בהמה מן האיל או
מן הכבש, Omer harei alai olat behema min ha-ayil o min ha-keves,
I will bring an עולה, olah, it will either be a ram
or a sheep. Okay, now everybody knows that a ram is an
adult male sheep, right? Okay, so I will bring an עולה, olah,
it will either be a ram or a sheep. Now the problem
is what defines a sheep, a lamb let's say, up to twelve
months? What defines a ram, thirteen months and older? So we have
this very clear middle category of between twelve months and thirteen months,
for that one month, and that's called a פלגס. palgas.
Okay, you see, you know, I'm a little overwhelmed here. To think
that someone, the farmer, actually knows exactly, exactly when each animal was
born.
Yeah, that's an, that's a good question, when it comes to bringing
a קרבן, korban, how would they know, could they make assumptions based
on physical characteristics?
They had flocks, you know.
Yeah, it's a very good question and being totally not being a
shepherd or a farmer, I have no idea. My, you know, my
guess would be that they would be like if it was obvious
based on physical characteristics, they can make reasonable assumptions based on those
in terms of
that's
a season.
That's what I
was going to say.
But it matters, a few days could still matter. Okay, I don't
know. It's a good question. What, check the teeth? You can check
how many months old they are by their teeth?
They come out at a- every what?
Every year? Every month? Every what?
Every day and they check?
Okay, so I'm sure they had ways, okay, and if not, I'm
sure there were physical characteristics that could give them a rough estimate.
No, and they just kept the yearling in one pen and then
the two-year.
All right, so now, so now
we have this question about again, this middle category. Is between twelve
months and thirteen months, and we can guess, you know, look, if
you look at a ram, it looks very different than a sheep,
right? So we can guess again not being- not knowing this, not
being a farmer or anything, but we can guess that during the
period that there's a transition period, right? Essentially an adolescence period where
it's getting some more of these adult physical characteristics but have not
fully developed. Presumably that's between the twelve months and thirteen months, in
this one month. So again the question is: Is this one month
definitely a ram or a sheep, we just don't know where to
draw the line, or no, it is actually
its own category, not a ram, not a sheep? So that's the
question. So somebody says I will bring an- I will bring an
עולה olah either as a- from a ram or from a sheep,
והביא פלגס, v'heivi palgas, and he brings this פלגס palgas which is
the word for this animal that is twelve months and not yet
thirteen months. Okay, מהו? mahu? What's the story? אליבא דרבי יוחנן לא
תיבעי לך דאמר בריה. Aliba d'Rabbi Yochanan lo tiba'ei lach d'amar beryah.
According to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, we'll see in a minute, he
says it's its own creature, meaning it's its own state. And therefore
clearly you didn't satisfy your obligation cause it's not a ram and
it's not a sheep. But there will be an opinion that we
want to know whether it's considered- that it may be it is
one or the other. So let's take a look. Who is this
רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? הוי? Havi? דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the
משנה: Mishna: הקריבו, Hikrivo, if you bring this פלגס palgas as a
sacrifice. Now remember, the תורה, Torah, we just read the other this
שבת Shabbos in פנחס, Pinchas, that the תורה Torah says that you
bring different מנחות נסכים, menachot nesachim, flour and wine based on what
type- what type of animal it is. If it's a sheep you
bring one עשרון, issaron, if it is a ram you bring two
עשרונות isronot of flour. Okay, similarly by the wine. If it's a
sheep you bring a quarter of a הין, hin, three לוג. log.
If it's a ram you bring four לוג, log, a third of
a הין. hin. So you bring this animal which is a פלגס,
palgas, right there between the sheep and the ram. Now first of
all I should say the fascinating thing is, is that it's a
כשר קרבן, kasher korban, right? You might have said if the תורה
Torah says you can bring a קרבן korban that's a כבש keves
and you can bring a קרבן korban that's an איל, ayil, that
maybe if it's neither one nor the other, you know, even if
it's falling in the middle, maybe it's not even a valid קרבן.
korban. Right? The גמרא Gemara doesn't you know does not really sort
of seem to
be suggesting that, but that's certainly a reasonable thing to think. If
it's not a כבש keves and not an איל, ayil, maybe it's
a פסול קרבן. pasul korban.
כחזי יומיה וחלה ירצה הכבש
לפני ה׳. Kechazi yomei v'chala yeirtzeh hakeves lifnei Hashem.
Understand, but doesn't mean that every animal can satisfy every requirement. Right?
Some animals have to be male, some have to be female. I
understand, but I'm saying if the תורה Torah says when you bring
an עולה olah it has to be a כבש keves or it
has to be a this, so it's not satisfying those criteria. Anyway,
interestingly that doesn't seem to bother the גמרא. Gemara. What seems to
bother the גמרא Gemara though is just like if it satisfies your
vow or in this case, does it- what type of מנחת נסכים
minchat nesachim do you bring with it? Do you bring the smaller
amount of flour and wine or the larger amount of flour and
wine? So here it was: You brought this פלגס, palgas, מעלה עליו
נסכי איל. ma'aleh alav niskei ayil. You bring the libations, the wine
and also the flour that's appropriate for the ram, the larger amount.
Okay. ואין עולה לו מזבחו, Ve-ein oleh lo mizivcho, but you do
not satisfy your obligation or your vow because you don't know if
this is a כבש keves or an איל, ayil, and you need
a כבש keves or an איל ayil to satisfy a vow. So
again the fascinating assumption is, is that if it's not a כבש
keves and not an איל ayil it doesn't satisfy any requirement. But
it still is a כשר קרבן, kasher korban, you don't know which
type of wine or flour to bring, you bring the larger amount.
Now the question we're asking is, is this because it is a
doubt which it is or because it definitely is a real category?
So let's take a look. ואמר רבי יוחנן, Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan, so
Rabbi Yochanan says, או לאיל, o la'ayil, the verse says again which
we just read on שבת, Shabbos, 'or for a ram' you should
bring so much wine and so much flour. לרבות את הפלגס, Lerabbos
es hapalgas, the extra word או לאיל o la'ayil means even something
that's not yet fully a ram, even a פלגס. palgas. So we're
back to our assumption that if the verse is needed to relate
to this state, it means it's not a doubt. If it was
a doubt, then the verse—think of the verse as the law book,
right? The verse is telling you there's a הלכה halacha for a
ram, there's הלכה halacha for a sheep. You don't know how to
categorize this, that's your problem, figure out how to deal with this
if you don't know what category to put it in. But if
the verse itself is addressing this state, then the assumption is that
it's a separate state. So it's telling you there's ram, there's sheep,
there's פלגס. palgas. פלגס Palgas you bring the amount of flour and
wine that's appropriate for a ram. So the fact that the verse
is relating to it indicates that it's its own category. So from
Rabbi Yochanan, he learns that you know you bring the flour and
wine appropriate for a ram based on a verse. For him it
seems clear, the גמרא Gemara assumes that this is its own category
which is just for the law of the flour and wine being
given the same law as that of the ram. Okay, so that's
we know for Rabbi Yochanan it's its own category. כי תיבעי לך
אליבא דבר פדא, Ki tiba'ei lach aliba deBar Pada, our question is
according to Bar Pada. דאמר, De'amar, who says, top of כג עמוד
ב, ka-gimmel amud beis, מייתי ומתני. maisei umasnei. You bring the flour
and the wine and you stipulate. Meaning according to Bar Pada, here's
what he says. He says: I don't know if this פלגס palgas
is a ram or a sheep. So what am I going to
do? I'll bring the flour and the wine and I'll make a
stipulation and I'll say: If this is a ram, then I'm bringing
the wine and the flour, the bigger amount appropriate for a ram.
If this is a sheep, then the subset of the wine and
the flour that's appropriate for the sheep, that's the right קרבן מנחת
נסכים. korban minchas nesachim. The extra amount of wine and flour, that's
just an extra קרבן, korban, that's just an independent, you know,
קרבן korban for the מזבח, mizbei'ach, it is not part of this
sheep. So you bring the larger amount. Yeah, so תוספות Tosafos deals
with questions about that if it's a מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim you
don't do קמיצה, kmitza, if it's its own מנחה mincha you do
do קמיצה. kmitza. So he says: Okay, but you can also vow
to bring a מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim by itself, not as a
straight מנחה. mincha. So that's what you're vowing. Well yes, תוספות Tosafos
actually does have it that way, yeah. I'm not getting into those
details, but Michael is correct to ask that it's not exactly a
subset. First of all, if the extra is extra, you might have
to treat it differently. So תוספות Tosafos says: No, you can say
it's the same type of a thing. The subset here is the
מנחת נסכים, minchas nesachim, the extra is a gift of a מנחת
נסכים, minchas nesachim, but not the מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim that goes
with the animal. The other question that תוספות Tosafos also asks, since
Michael raises it, is that
the proportion of flour to oil that you mix in this מנחה
mincha differs between a sheep and a ram. So it's not really
true that it's a subset, right? Wine you could say either a
lot of wine, a little wine, it's a subset. But if it's
the question about the flour and oil mix, they're different types of
mixtures. So תוספות Tosafos says: Okay, you bring two types of mixtures
and you say, you know, if it's a ram the bigger mixture
is for the ram, the smaller is its own קרבן, korban, and
if it's a sheep the smaller mixture is for the sheep and
the bigger one is its own קרבן. korban. Okay, so that's what
he says. He says it's one or the other. So you don't
just סתם stam bring it, it's not like the verse tells you
give it the law of the ram in terms of the oil
and the flour. It's that we don't know, so you make a
stipulation, whichever one it is, that's how the flour and oil and
wine work, and the rest is its own קרבן korban if needed.
Okay, so according to him it seems clear that it's a doubt.
So what's the issue according to him? מי אמרינן, Mi amrinan, do
we say
איל וכבש מתנה, ayil vecheves masna, בבריה לא מתנה, bebirya lo masna,
that your stipulation is: if it's a ram then this should be
the flour and the wine, and if it's a sheep then this
should be the flour and the wine, but regarding בריה, birya, regarding
a third possibility that it's its own category, you don't stipulate? או
דלמא, O dilma, or possibly
בבריה נמי מתנה, bebirya nami masna, part of your stipulation includes the
possibility that this פלגס palgas is its own category. And what would
you say then? So if you don't have the verse, Rabbi Yochanan
had a verse that tells you here's what you do for a
פלגס, palgas, you give it the מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim of an
איל. ayil. But according to Bar Pada, he doesn't have a special
verse. So what would he do if it's genuinely its own category?
It wouldn't have a מנחת נסכים. minchas nesachim. And here would be
your stipulation: דאמר, De'amar, you would say, אי בריה הוי, ei birya
havei, if it's its own category, להוי כולה נדבה, lehavei kula nedava,
all the flour I'm bringing and all the wine I'm bringing should
be a pure gift, right? It's not obligatory at all because the
Torah says: Here's what you do for a ram, here's what you
do for a sheep. This which is neither ram nor sheep has
no מנחת נסכים, minchas nesachim, it has no flour, it has no
wine. So therefore this that I'm bringing should not be part of
the animal, it should be its own gift, its own sacrifice. תיקו,
Teiku, so we don't know. So here again very much parallel to
the issue of the adolescence by the birds, you have adolescence by
sheep, the transition of sheep to ram, and again, what is fascinating
is that the גמרא Gemara assumes that in this middle stage, it
didn't seem to assume this by birds. By birds, it assumes that
if you brought a bird in this תחילת הציהוב techilat hatziuv period,
this adolescent period, it's invalid. It's a פסול קרבן. pasul korban. Here
it seems to assume it's acceptable as a קרבן, korban, but it
doesn't satisfy your requirement. The תורה Torah demands either a ram or
a sheep, or your vow would obligate you in a ram or
a sheep, not in a middle thing, but it would be a
legitimate קרבן, korban, which you didn't satisfy your requirements. And the question
would be, what type of מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim would you bring
with it? The one appropriate for ram, the one appropriate for sheep?
So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan understands that it's its own category, and
the verse is just assigning it the מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim of
the ram, but it's its own category. The question is בר פדא.
Bar Pada. בר פדא Bar Pada says it's a doubt. Well, does
the doubt include the possibility of its own category or is the
doubt only that it's either ram or sheep but for him he's
certain that it's not an independent category, and the גמרא Gemara doesn't
know.
Yes, both agree it's not valid though to fulfill your vow?
Yes, yes, that's taken for granted. Okay, so that's those questions about
middle stages, adolescent animals for קרבנות. korbanot. Now we're going to ask
another related קרבן korban question, but again, all around this question of
middle categories. בעי רבי זירא. baei Rabbi Zeira. So רבי זירא Rabbi
Zeira also asked. רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira seemed to have liked this.
Notice that he's the one asking the questions. So he asks the
following thing. האומר הרי עלי לחמי תודה מן החמץ או מן המצה
והביא שיאור מהו. Haomer harei alai lachmei todah min hachametz o min
hamatzah vehevi se'or mahu. So again, finding a case where A is
good, B is good, but what about the space between A and
B? So for bread of a תודה, todah, you bring 30 loaves
of מצה, matzah, 10 loaves of חמץ. chametz. Let's say somebody accepts
upon himself the obligation to bring bread of a תודה todah
and now again, the גמרא Gemara is going to have to construct
the case where if you had to bring all the bread of
the תודה, todah, then you would have to bring things that you
knew were מצה matzah and things you knew were חמץ, chametz, you
wouldn't know you fulfilled your obligation, but the person somehow stipulated that
I'm going to bring one of the sets of 10 loaves of
תודה, todah, somehow we'll make that stipulation, we'll see how in a
minute, 10 loaves that would be good for a תודה todah he's
going to bring that. So if they were all מצה matzah that
would be good, if they were all חמץ chametz that would be
good. Instead what he brings is he brings שיאור, se'or, when they
basically have started to ferment. Okay, so in this state where the
fermenting has begun, they're not exactly חמץ, chametz, not exactly מצה. matzah.
Are they one or the other and we just don't know how
to categorize, and then he would satisfy his obligation? Or are they
neither, and it's neither חמץ, chametz, neither מצה matzah and he did
not satisfy his obligation? Now what is the stage of שיאור? se'or?
So for us, when we talk about מצה, matzah, we turn it
into a time period. 18 minutes, by the way, 18 minutes means
let alone outside of the oven without being worked, meaning once it
starts cooking you obviously the clock stops. I know obviously I don't
think people are always aware of that, and also as long as
you're still working the dough, it's not considered to have the opportunity
to ferment. So our 18 minutes is basically you're leaving the dough
not being cooked without working it gives it the time to ferment.
But in the גמרא Gemara the time, that's just because we are
like we're so detached from our sort of physical realities in so
many ways. So we always have to find a way that we
can just quantify it and translate it into something measurable like time.
The גמרא Gemara primarily talks about whether something is חמץ chametz or
not based on its physical appearance and talks about the fact that
when the dough starts crusting over, that's one stage, and then it's
when that crust actually develops cracks in it, that's another stage. Now
what is the issue about שיאור? se'or? So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is the strict position. He says it is considered to be beginning
to ferment, שיאור se'or maybe call it sourdough, at the early stage,
as soon as the dough crusts over, number one. He's also strict
that he says that at that stage, if you were to eat
that on פסח, Pesach, you wouldn't get כרת, kareth, but you would
get lashes. It's a type of a חמץ chametz and you would
get lashes. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is lenient in two ways. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda first of
all says to me it's not even an issue until it starts
cracking. Prior to the cracking of the crust, it's not even a
problem at all. And even when it cracks, you only—you shouldn't eat
it on פסח, Pesach, but you don't even get lashes. So what
is it? Is it some rabbinic problem? Is it a biblical problem?
But it's certainly not yet חמץ, chametz, it's something else. But that's
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda both has it as
a later stage and he says you don't even get lashes. So
now the question is going to be when we ask whether this
שיאור se'or is considered to be חמץ chametz or not, who are
you asking according to? Because it would seem that based on who
you ask and what stage, the answer will be different. So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says: So what's the law
if you bring this שיאור se'or for either breads of חמץ chametz
or breads of
מצה? matzah? The גמרא Gemara says: שיאור דמאן כי שיאור אי שיאור
דרבי מאיר לרבי יהודה se'or deman kei se'or i se'or deRabbi Meir
leRabbi Yehuda and you want to know from רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda
perspective what stage... the status when before the cracks, when it just
began to crust. So that's clear, מצה מעליא היא! matzah malyasa hi!
It's total מצה! matzah! He says it's not even an issue until
it begins to crack, so there's no doubt. Okay, so let's try
the reverse. אי דרבי יהודה לרבי מאיר, Ee de'Rebbi Yehuda le'Rebbi Meir,
maybe the opposite. רבי יהודה'ס Rebbi Yehuda's state, right, where it where
it begins to crack according to רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. And we
want to know, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir remember says it's a problem
as soon as it crusts. What would he say when the cracks
begin? So the גמרא Gemara says, well that's obvious also. So אי
דרבי יהודה לרבי מאיר, ee de'Rebbi Yehuda le'Rebbi Meir, if it's the
cracked state for רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir who's the stricter one, חמץ
הוא, chametz hu, that's definitely חמץ. chametz. So obviously to ask how
they would work in their cross states is obviously for רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda an earlier state is obviously completely non-problematic and for רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir a later state is completely חמץ. chametz. Okay, so
let's try this
way. ואי דרבי מאיר לרבי מאיר, Ve'ee de'Rebbi Meir le'Rebbi Meir, that
seems like the one to ask, right? Because רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
says when it begins to crust, you get lashes for eating it
on פסח, Pesach, but you don't get כרת. kares. So that's the
interesting state. What does that mean that you get lashes and not
כרת? kares? Is it חמץ chametz or not חמץ? chametz? If it's
חמץ, chametz, why don't you get כרת? kares? If it's not חמץ,
chametz, why do you get lashes? So maybe that's the one that's
the interesting state. So the גמרא Gemara says, if that's what you're
asking, אי
דרבי מאיר לרבי מאיר, ee de'Rebbi Meir le'Rebbi Meir, מדלקי ליה midelaki
lei since you get lashes, חמץ הוא, chametz hu, it's definitely חמץ.
chametz. Now תוספות Tosafos is not so happy with this assumption. תוספות
Tosafos says who says? If it really were חמץ, chametz, you should
get כרת. kares. Okay, so how do you assume that just because
you get lashes it's חמץ? chametz? Maybe the very fact that it's
lashes and not כרת kares means it's something that's not חמץ chametz
and not מצה. matzah. So רש"י Rashi tries to answer it by
saying yes, you really should get כרת. kares. The only reason you
don't get כרת kares is because it's not really fit to be
eaten. It's not ראוי לאכילה rauy le'achila yet. So it's like a
technical problem. In terms of the fermenting, it's fully חמץ. chametz. But
in terms of did you eat something that's real food, it's not
yet real food because it's not yet ראוי לאכילה. rauy le'achila. It's
not fit because it's like still like it's very sourdough. It's called
sourdough for a reason, right? It's like no, it's not
like eating raw dough.
Well you could have baked it afterwards. But I think the assumption
here is that you're eating it raw, correct. What? Why is that
the assumption? Because when we refer to שיאור, se'ur, we're usually referring
to the dough state, the sourdough state.
No, aren't we just describing the dough right before it goes in
the oven?
You could say that, but the assumption here is that we're talking
about the dough.
So it says you go crack or you left it out long
enough.
Yes, right. Okay. So anyway, that's what רש"י Rashi says. תוספות Tosafos
is really bothered by it. תוספות Tosafos really thinks that maybe it's
a special חומרא chumra by פסח. Pesach. Maybe the תורה Torah is
more, has a broader category by פסח. Pesach. Maybe, and that's why,
but because it's broader than normal, that's why on the one hand
you get lashes, but on the other hand you don't get כרת.
kares. And maybe in other areas of הלכה, halacha, the category would
be the more smaller, more normal category and it wouldn't be חמץ
chametz at all. And תוספות Tosafos tries to answer it, but he
really is left with his
question. But they're lashes מן התורה. min ha'Torah. Okay, but it's just
that you have a broader definition by פסח. Pesach. Which is, they're
clearly מן התורה. min ha'Torah. Which really is very interesting because it
also raises the question of that when we deal with these states
and these questionable how do you categorize them, the answer might be
different based on different areas of הלכה. halacha. So for example, right,
maybe in certain areas of הלכה halacha you categorize adolescence as childhood
and other areas of הלכה halacha you categorize adolescence as adulthood. It's
not that there's an objective reality it's one or the other. Right,
sort of going back to other discussions we had the other day
about brain death or whatever. It's a legal question. How do you
categorize it? So maybe it's its own category, maybe it's subsumed in
other categories, and maybe it depends on which category of הלכה halacha
you're talking, you know, which sphere of הלכה halacha you're talking about.
So that's תוספות's Tosafos's question. תוספות Tosafos says why don't we say
exactly this? That since maybe by פסח Pesach we have a broader
definition and that allows you to get מלקות, malkos, but it's not
prime חמץ, chametz, which is why you don't get כרת, kares, and
maybe therefore for other הלכות halachos we should see it as non-חמץ.
chametz. So תוספות Tosafos does not really resolve that, or he tries
to resolve it, but the question is stronger than the answer. Okay,
so that's the גמרא Gemara at least assumes since you're getting מלקות
malkos it is some form of חמץ chametz and it is not
in this doubtful category. So let's try to look how the גמרא
Gemara does try to ultimately frame its question. אלא דרבי יהודה לרבי
יהודה. Ela de'Rebbi Yehuda le'Rebbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה'ס שיאור Rebbi Yehuda's se'ur
according to רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. When it begins to crust and
not crack yet, and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says, I'm sorry, I
said that wrong. Only when it cracks, only at a later stage,
and even there רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says you don't get lashes.
מאי? Mai? So since you don't get lashes but he says it's
forbidden to eat, so that's the גמרא Gemara says that's an interesting
middle state, right? Because if you get lashes, clearly there's an element
of חמץ chametz in it. That's what the גמרא Gemara just said.
But if you don't get lashes, then what are we saying? Are
we saying it's מצה matzah but we don't like you eating it?
Are we saying it's חמץ chametz but not real חמץ? chametz? I
mean what are we saying? What does that mean don't eat it
but don't get lashes? So that's what we want to know, according
to him what is the status of this sour bread when it
cracks that he says you don't get lashes but but it's forbidden
to eat? Is it חמץ chametz or is it מצה? matzah? מאי?
Mai? What's the status? ספיקא הוי? Sfeika havei? Is it a doubt
how to
categorize? it's
either
חמץ *chametz* or מצה *matzah*, we just don't know. So since it's
one or the other, on the one hand Rabbi Yehuda says I'm
not going to give you lashes, on the other hand he says
don't eat it, because he doesn't know how to categorize it. או
דילמא *o dilma*, or do we say, בריה הוא *birya hu*, it's
right in that space, the gap between חמץ *chametz* and מצה *matzah*.
So since it's not מצה *matzah*, you can't eat it on פסח
*Pesach*, but since it's not חמץ *chametz*, you don't get lashes. And
if it's right in that gap, therefore לא נפיק *lo nafiq*, you
don't satisfy your obligation when you try to bring it for the
breads of the תודה *todah*. Okay, so there the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
ends that—I mean, we're now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to
figure out how you made your vow, but that's the framing of
the question. So everybody understands this? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this: According to Rabbi Meir, this sourdough, if you get lashes, clearly
there's an element of real חמץ *chametz* here. Maybe it's not 100%
חמץ *chametz*, but there's an element of real חמץ *chametz* and therefore
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* thinks that that at least resolves the question,
although as I said, תוספות *Tosafot* says maybe not, you're not getting
כרת *kares*, whatever. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* thinks the better way—the
better possibility, the way I'll—let me actually rephrase this because there's one
element which תוספות *Tosafot* says which makes it better. He says like
this: According to Rabbi Meir, since you're getting lashes, maybe it's not
fully חמץ *chametz*, but there's one thing I can tell you that
it isn't if you're getting lashes: מצה *matzah*. And the—exactly. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*—so maybe it's not חמץ *chametz*, but it's certainly not
מצה *matzah* if you're getting lashes. And the גמרא *Gemara* wants to
talk about a case where it might be מצה *matzah*, might be
חמץ *chametz*, it might be one, it might be the other. And
this thing, if you're getting lashes, you're certainly not מצה *matzah*. That's
what תוספות *Tosafot* actually says to make the גמרא *Gemara* better. Although
the גמרא *Gemara* says it's definitely חמץ *chametz*, תוספות *Tosafot* like rephrases
the גמרא *Gemara* for Rabbi Meir and says it's certainly not מצה
*matzah*. Which means you can't bring it, which is why we're passing—we're
not framing it within Rabbi Meir. So yes, you get lashes, maybe
it's not full חמץ *chametz*, but you know what, it's certainly not
מצה *matzah*. But according to Rabbi Yehuda you could ask either way,
because Rabbi Yehuda says don't eat it but you don't get lashes.
So like there's no consequence. So what does that mean? So that's
the possible to say that maybe it really is מצה *matzah*, but
we don't know. On the one hand, maybe it's מצה *matzah*, so
I'm not going to give you lashes, on the other hand, maybe
it's חמץ *chametz*, so I'm going to tell you not to eat
it. It's one or the other, I just don't know. Or do
we say it's a middle state, and because it's the middle state,
that's why don't eat it but don't get lashes. So within Rabbi
Yehuda you really have the possibility it could be either one or
the other and that's how we're framing our question. But again, as
I said, what is interesting is thinking about this issue of that
maybe how we define something as A or B or whatever might
depend on which area of הלכה *halakha*, maybe some areas, you know,
define their categories differently. Anyway, let's see how the גמרא *Gemara* finishes
this up with the תודה *todah*. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says: ואמר
רב הונא *ve-amar Rav Huna*, didn't רב הונא *Rav Huna* say: האומר
הרי עלי לחמי תודה מביא תודה ולחמה *ha-omer harei alai lachmei todah
meivi todah ve-lachmah*? How can you obligate yourself just in the bread
of a תודה *todah*? רב הונא *Rav Huna* says if you obligate
yourself in the bread of a תודה *todah*, since bread of a
תודה *todah* does not come by itself, you implicitly have to bring
the תודה *todah* as well. And since you have to bring the
תודה *todah* as well, you have to bring 30 things that are
definitely מצה *matzah* and 10 things that are definitely חמץ *chametz*. You
can't bring this doubtful thing because you won't know which category it
fell in. So how do you solve it? וכיון דחייב ליה בתודה
ולחמה *ve-kivan de-chayiv lei be-todah ve-lachmah*, since you're obligated in the תודה
*todah* and its bread, הא לא ידע האי גברא *ha lo yada
hai gavra* אי חמץ הוא *i chametz hu* דליתי מצה *de-lei-tei matzah*,
you don't know if this sourdough is חמץ *chametz* that now you
have to—what you're left to bring is your מצה *matzah*, אי מצה
הוא *i matzah hu* or whether it's the מצה *matzah* bread, דליתי
חמץ *de-lei-tei chametz*, and what you're left to bring is חמץ *chametz*.
So if you have to bring the full complement, 30 מצה *matzah*
and 10 חמץ *chametz*, bringing things that are doubtful does not help
you because since you don't know which category they fall in, you're
certainly going to have to bring all 30 מצה *matzah* and all
10 חמץ *chametz* because you don't know which category you exempted yourself
from. So the שיאור *se-or* just whatever, either as a קרבן *korban*
or a איסור *issur*, but the point is there wouldn't be a
question here because
you—since even if it was a ספק *sufek*, since you don't know
which category you exempted yourself from, you're no better off. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says: לא, צריכא *lo, tzericha*, no, you need it for
the case דאמר הרי עלי חלה לפטור תודתו של פלוני *de-amar harei
alai challah li-ftor todato shel ploni*. You do not obligate yourself in
a תודה *todah*, you obligated yourself to bring the חלה *challah* for
somebody else's תודה *todah*. Michael here is bringing a תודה *todah* and
I say—well, we're going to see. Michael here is bringing a תודה
*todah* and I say: You know what, Michael, I'm going to do
you a favor. I'm going to bring ten loaves to give for
your תודה *todah*, okay? So I'm going to—it'll either be the מצה
*matzah* loaves or the חמץ *chametz* loaves, I'm going to bring ten
of those loaves and you won't have to bring them. And I
go ahead and I bring the ten of שיאור *se-or*. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says: Okay, but it still doesn't help it because Michael
doesn't know whether I've gotten him out of חמץ *chametz*—his חמץ *chametz*
obligation or מצה *matzah* obligation. He's still going to have to bring
his full 40 loaves. So even if it's a doubt A or
B, how've I solved anything? Since you don't know which one it
is, his obligation remains full and I've vowed to exempt him from
part of his obligation. Well, I haven't exempted him because I haven't
practically solved his problem, okay?
So give you lashes? No.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says: סוף סוף *sof sof*, says the גמרא
*Gemara* at the end of the day, הא לא ידע האי גברא
*ha lo yada hai gavra* אי חמץ הוא *i chametz hu* דליתי
מצה *de-lei-tei matzah* מאי *mai* you don't know, Michael, if this was
חמץ *chametz* that now what you're left to, left over is to
bring the מצה *matzah* or if I've brought מצה *matzah* and what
you have left to do is to bring the חמץ *chametz*. So
if I say I'm going to bring loaves to exempt you and
I don't effectively exempt him because he doesn't know how to categorize
it, obviously we haven't gotten anywhere.
And he helps himself there?
What? Well, that is interesting that the גמרא *Gemara* could have suggested
it. What was that? That maybe that I helped myself. My vow
was to exempt him from ten of his loaves. So if we
say that this is a ספק *safek*, not a בריה *biryah*, it's
not a middle state, it really is either חמץ *chametz* or מצה
*matzah* we just don't know, then maybe what you could say is
look, you know, I said I would bring ten loaves towards his
obligation. They were towards his obligation. The fact that he doesn't know
which part of his obligation it exempted him from, that's his problem.
So he's going to have to bring all the loaves, but did
I objectively bring ten loaves towards his obligation? Yes. So that's actually
the גמרא *Gemara* could have said that. Interestingly it didn't. Presumably the
גמרא *Gemara* understands that if I say לפטור *liftoor* to exempt you,
I mean to practically exempt you, not just to objectively count it
towards it. But the גמרא *Gemara*'s answer is going to be more
or less that. So let's see what the גמרא *Gemara*'s answer is.
לא, צריכא דלא אמר לפטור *lo, tsricha delo amar liftoor*. I didn't
say I was going to bring loaves to exempt Michael. I said
I will bring ten of Michael's loaves. Okay, and I didn't say
for the purpose of exempting him. Michael has to bring a תודה
*todah*. I agree to bring ten of those loaves. So מפיק ידי
נדרו, נפיק או לא נפיק *mapik yedei nidro, nafik o lo nafik*.
תיקו *teiku*. Did I satisfy my vow or not? If these loaves
of sourdough are neither חמץ *chametz* nor מצה *matzah*, I did not
bring ten of his loaves. If they are either חמץ *chametz* or
מצה *matzah*, I just don't know which one, so he still has
to bring all forty because he doesn't know which one I've done.
But my vow to bring ten of those loaves, I did satisfy
those vow because I did bring ten of those loaves, we just
don't know which ten. So the גמרא *Gemara* leaves this as a
doubt. So again, this is a third category the same way we
dealt with age, adolescence, by birds and by animals, is it adulthood
or childhood we just don't know or is it its own category.
Now we're dealing with this sourdough. Is it unleavened or leavened and
we just don't know which category to put it in, but it's
either leavened or unleavened or no, it's a middle state between leavened
and unleavened and it's its own thing. So therefore, if it's this
middle state, it would never count towards the breads of a תודה
*todah*. If it's one or the other we just don't know which
one, it would count towards ten, we just don't know which ten.
But if we don't know
then in the end he has to, you would have to, but
I would satisfy my vow. Now again, I do want to point
out to remind some interesting characteristics that we did say here about
this was
I forgot the point I was going to make.
Oh yes, the point that exactly this, that
if it is this doubtful thing, so the question is, if it
is this middle step, stage, what does that mean? Does it mean
it's totally invalid or does it just mean I don't fulfill my
obligation? Right, again what's fascinating here is is that, you know, you
might have said that for example by the birds, if the birds
are in this state of adolescence, it seems like they're invalid as
sacrifices. When the sheep is in this adolescence between sheep and ram,
it seems like it's a valid קרבן *korban*, we just it just
doesn't satisfy any vow, any obligation, but it's a valid קרבן *korban*.
These loaves here, right, again the emphasis here on the question was,
was it did it satisfy my vow, again an assumption being that
it would be a valid as a as an offering, it just
doesn't satisfy my vow. But that's not so clear because if you
say that it's a בריה *biryah*, it's its own thing and it's
not brought in the context of לחמי תודה *lachmei todah*, then I
think it would be very questionable whether it would even be a
valid קרבן *korban*. So within this middle state, what are the consequences
of it is also, you know, also seems to differ from from
one to the other. The final point thing I'll point out which
I was expecting you to ask Michael is that you can't have
the ten loaves be either חמץ *chametz* or מצה *matzah* because as
we learned in מנחות *Menachot*, right, the quantity of flour is different.
The amount of for the מצה *matzah* loaves, each מצה *matzah* loaf
is only a third of the flour of the חמץ *chametz* loaf.
So how can you have ten loaves which will either count as
one or the other you just don't know since the quantity of
flour is different. So I don't know the answer to that question.
תוספות *Tosafot* actually does ask it, but that is something also to
ask. Anyway, we are done now with this for now. But this
as I think is a great question in so many different categories
which is how do you do with these middle stages. One very
common one is for example בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*, right, or right
the period between sunset and the stars coming out, dusk. Right, is
dusk either night or day we just don't know which one, or
really is its own thing, neither night nor day. And therefore we
have to give it special הלכות halachot *halachot* because we can't categorize
it either as night or as day. Similarly you could ask from
the period between the morning star and sunrise, right, what do we
call that, dawn? I guess it's called dawn, right? So not so
that's called is that normally we're taught that that's considered to be
day, but there are things you're not supposed to do from the
morning star, right, the questions about, you know, making a ברכה *bracha*.
So normally we explain that those are rabbinic concerns, that you might
not be confused about the time, but Rav Soloveitchik, for example, says,
no, to some way it's a parallel of בין השמשות, not the
same, but there's some parallel and that that's really is its own
state. It's neither—it's neither night nor day. It's this period between night
and day, and the opposite end, when it's coming to be day
rather, when it's whatever. And therefore, it has its own הלכות halachot
that you're not supposed to do day מצוות mitzvot לכתחילה, lechatchila, but
בדיעבד bediavad they count. Okay, so if it is a middle state,
then you have to figure out what are the הלכות that apply
to this middle state. But this is in general a very important
question when something is falls between A and B, is it one
or the other we don't know which, or is it its own
state. Do you ever feel the same thing like, let's say, of
an—or a boy, whatever—like twelve, twelve and a half doesn't have שתי
שערות? shtei searot? Yeah, could be. You have to ask in each
category. Some have very clear lines, it's either all or nothing, and
some have acknowledged middle states. And the question is, when we—there is
a middle state, is it generally its own state or is it
that we don't know how to categorize? So that's the question here.
Let's begin now the next משנה, mishna, again, with this idea that
what works for A doesn't work for B. כשר בפרה פסול בעגלה.
kasher beparah pasul be'eglah. So two types of animals, just that are—you
do rituals with them outside of the מקדש. Mikdash. פרה אדומה parah
adumah and the עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah, and they're both cows, right?
One is a calf and the other is a cow. So what
you do for a cow you don't do for the—for the עגלה.
eglah. What do you do for the cow, the פרה אדומה? parah
adumah? You שחט shecht it. What do you do for the עגלה
ערופה? eglah arufah? You break its neck. It's sort of like the
parallel to the issue about שחיטה shechitah and מליקה melikah by the
birds, right? The שחט-ing shecht with the knife from the—from this part
and the מליקה melikah from the back. So here too, what you
do for the פרה אדומה parah adumah is you שחט, shecht, what
you do for the עגלה eglah is you break its neck. What
you do for the פרה parah is invalid for the עגלה.
eglah. If you שחט-ed shecht an עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah, it would
not be כשר. kasher. כשר בעגלה, kasher be'eglah, what you do for
the עגלה, eglah, which is breaking the neck, פסול בפרה, pasul beparah,
you can't do for the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. Okay. תנו רבנן,
tanu rabanan, our rabbis taught, פרה בשחיטה כשרה בעריפה פסולה. parah bishchitah
kesherah ba'arifah pesulah. פרה parah is good if you שחט shecht it,
not if you break its neck. עגלה, eglah, the calf, right, when
you don't know who the murderer is, בעריפה כשרה בשחיטה פסולה. ba'arifah
kesherah bishchitah pesulah. It's good for breaking—when you break the neck, it's
invalid when you שחט. shecht. נמצא, nimtza, so this is what the
משנה mishna teaches, כשר בפרה פסול בעגלה כשר בעגלה פסול בפרה. kasher
beparah pasul be'eglah kasher be'eglah pasul beparah. Okay, what's good for one
is not good for the other. So now the גמרא asks one
of its classic קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ודהא פרה כשרה בעריפה מקל
וחומר. vedeha parah kesherah ba'arifah mikal vachomer. Why not say you can
do the breaking of the neck by a פרה אדומה parah adumah
from a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? What's the קל וחומר? kal vachomer?
ומה עגלה שלא הוכשרה בשחיטה הוכשרה בעריפה. umah eglah shelo huchsharah bishchitah
huchsharah ba'arifah. An עגלה ערופה eglah arufah which you can't שחט, shecht,
you have to break its neck, you can only do the breaking
of the neck, פרה שהוכשרה בשחיטה אינו דין שהוכשרה בעריפה. parah shehuchsharah
bishchitah eino din shehuchsharah ba'arifah. פרה parah that you can do שחיטה,
shechitah, certainly you should be able to do what—you could break the
neck. So אמר קרא, amar kra, so just the beginning of the
פסוק pasuk says, ושחט וחוקה. veshachat vechukah. It says you should שחט
shecht it by the פרה אדומה parah adumah and it says that
זאת חוקת, zot chukat, it uses the phrase חוק. chok. בשחיטה אין
בעריפה לא. bishchitah in ba'arifah lo. Only שחיטה, shechitah, not breaking the
neck, only what it says. Okay, and then the גמרא is going
to continue with this tomorrow, so we'll worry about that tomorrow. I'll
just end you with this idea of the קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
These are the very frustrating קל וחומר, kal vachomer, right? Things which
we assume that these are unique to each one and the גמרא
creates a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, you know, oh, if it works
here then it should certainly work there. So I'll just tell you
the story. There was a ספר sefer called עצמות יוסף, Atzmot Yosef,
I think I've said this before, by a late אחרון acharon on
קידושין. Kiddushin. Anybody who's ever learned the first פרק perek of קידושין,
Kiddushin, it's like all of these דרשות drashot from פסוקים pesukim and
it's all these questions. Well, why don't we learn a קל וחומר?
kal vachomer? If this is what works by an עבד, eved, then
it should work for קידושין Kiddushin and it should work for this
and a קל וחומר kal vachomer like crosses categories. If it works
for A, it should work for B. So anyway, so as if
it's not bad enough in the גמרא, this person wrote this whole
ספר sefer where he like multiplies it ten times. That's all the
possibilities the גמרא didn't even bother asking. Okay, so that's his ספר.
sefer. Anyway, there was the story that he was once at somebody's
house for שבת Shabbat and they served him soup and they gave
him a fork. So he says, why do you give me a
fork? So the guy says, well, it's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
He says, when it comes to meat, he says, you can't eat
it with a spoon but you can eat it with a fork.
So soup, that you eat with a spoon, קל וחומר kal vachomer
you should be able to eat it with a fork, which is
exactly the problems in all of these קל וחומר, kal vachomer, which
is, you know, the whole point is that each thing is distinct.
Why should we assume that you can transfer? Which is in the
end what the גמרא says, but obviously we saw that before and
we will continue to see this tomorrow.